Schoharie Land Trust; Records apap160
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Schoharie Land Trust Records
1980-2001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Schoharie Land Trust
apap160
3 cubic ft. 26 Digital Files 2 videos, 1 audiotape
Founded in 1990 to to promote the preservation of agricultural, scenic, forest, natural, recreational, and open space land in Schoharie County.
Historical Note
The Schoharie Land Trust (SLT) was organized on June 25, 1990 by co-chairmen Bob Smith and Karl Westphal, as well as Kenneth Hotopp, Mary O'Donnell and other residents of Schoharie County. It became fully incorporated in 1991, with established by-laws and policies. Its purpose is to promote the preservation of agricultural, scenic, forest, natural, recreational, and open space land. Working with funds from donations and grants, the SLT seeks to acquire and manage property and conservation easements. It also seeks to increase the community appreciation of agricultural lands and rural communities. The SLT obtained non-profit status in 1992, and gained its first easement, the O'Donnell property, in 1995. SLT is based in Cobleskill, NY, and holds its meetings in the Cobleskill Public Library. It is a member of the American Farmland Trust and the Land Trust Alliance and has adopted the Alliance's 2004 Land Trust Standards and Practices.
Additional information about the history of the organization is available in Series 1 Box 1 Folder 31 "Official History."
Scope and Contents
The Schoharie Land Trust Records contain meeting minutes, agendas, correspondence, financial statements, by-laws, policies, reports, and membership records. The bulk of these records date from 1990 to 2001, and there are a few articles and publications dating back to the 1980's. The Records contain a strong collection of minutes from the original Steering Committee and the later Board of Directors and Acquisition Committee. Electronic versions of Steering Committee and Finance Committee minutes for the period 1990-1992 are available in electronic form.
Its efforts to preserve specific properties are documented in the Property Files series with maps, checklists, photographs, correspondence, and official deeds and easements. These files are erratic, with a great deal of information about a few properties and very little about many others. The best documented are the Paulson and the Schoharie Creek properties.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 3 file series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Schoharie Land Trust in 2003 June.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Agricultural conservation -- New York (State).; Environmental protection -- New York (State) -- Citizen participation.; Land trusts.; Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Minutes.; Agendas (administrative records); Correspondence.; Land use maps.; Deeds.; Easements.; Photographs.; Color slides.; Digital Files; Smith, Bob.; Westphal, Karl.; Hotopp, Kenneth.; ODonnell, Mary.; Schoharie Land Trust.; Land Trust Alliance.; American Farmland Trust.
- Administrative Files, 1980-2001; 1; 1 cubic ft. 26 Digital Files
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents relating to the operation of the Schoharie Land Trust, including correspondence, membership records, by-laws, policies, publications, committee reports, and meeting minutes. The meeting minutes begin in 1990 with the Steering Committee which became the Board of Directors with full incorporation in 1991. The records primarily begin in 1990 with the beginning of planning for the SLT, with a few articles and publications included from the 1980's.
  - Acquisition Committee, Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1992-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting, Minutes, Agendas, Reports, 1991-1993; 1995-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1991 May 16
    - Minutes, 1992 April 30
  - Annual Reports, 1992-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1989; 1992-1997; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Berdan, Leonard, Appraisal Qualifications, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Agendas, 1990-1993; 1995-1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Minutes, 1991-1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1990 June 25
    - Minutes, 1990 July 17
    - Minutes, 1990 August 14
    - Minutes, 1990 September 12
    - Minutes, 1990 October 10
    - Minutes, 1990 November 14
    - Minutes, 1990 December 12
    - Minutes, 1991 January 17
    - Minutes, 1991 April 18
    - Minutes, 1991 June 20
    - Minutes, 1991 July 18
    - Minutes, 1991 August 15
    - Minutes, 1991 September 19
    - Minutes, 1991 October 17
    - Minutes, 1991 December 19
    - Minutes, 1992 January 16
    - Minutes, 1992 March 19
    - Minutes, 1992 June 18
    - Minutes, 1992 July 16
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Minutes, 1997-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors, Member Information, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - By-laws, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1992 March 20
  - Correspondence, 1998-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, American Farmland Trust, 1991-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Drafts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Land Trust Alliance, 1992-1995; 1999-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Schoharie County Planning & Development Agency, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - County of Schoharie, Proposed Local Law to Establish the Office of County Manager & Proposed County Manager Selection Process, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Criteria for Land Acquisition, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Donor Lists, 2000; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Farr Committee, 1998-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Finance Committee, Meeting Minutes, 1992
    - Minutes, 1992 June 18
    - Minutes, 1992 June 18
    - Minutes, 1992 August 20
  - Leaflets, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Mailing Lists, 1990-1991; 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Meeting Notes, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Membership Applications and Renewals, 1991-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Membership Applications and Renewals, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Membership Applications and Renewals, 1999-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Membership Committee, 1994-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Membership Meeting, 1991
    - Minutes, 1991 November 21
  - NAFTA, Articles, Press Releases, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Newsletters, 1989; 1991-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Official History, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Open Space Preservation, Resolution of Board of Supervisors, Schoharie County, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Outline and Handouts for Presentation, Notes, Leaflets, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Photographs, 1994-2000; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Policies, 1997; 2000; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Position Descriptions, 1980; 1984; 1988-1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Project Proposals, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Publications, Cornell Cooperative Extension, 1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
  - Publications, Department of Environmental Conservation, 1991; 1995; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
  - Response to Request for Proposal, Daniel Goldstein & Associates, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
  - Schoharie County Agricultural & Farmland Protection Plan, Schoharie County Agricultural and Protection Board, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
  - Schoharie Master Plan, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - Slides, 1996; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 43)
  - Steering Committee, Meeting Minutes, Agendas, 1990-1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 44)
  - Tax Exempt Status, 501c3 Application Forms, Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 45)
  - Zoning Regulations, Town of Seward, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 46)
  - Land Trust Alliance, Rally 91: Tax Planning for Land Conservation Deals: War Stories and Other Observations, Audio Cassette, 1991 (Cassette 1)
  - Land Trust, Jerry Cosgrove, VHS, Undated (Vhs 1)
  - Farmland Forever, American Farmland Trust, VHS, Undated (Vhs 2)
- Grant Files, 1991-1998; 2; 1 cubic ft.
  This series consists of documents generated and collected by the Schoharie Land Trust in the search for funding through grants. The two largest sources of documents are the Federal Emergency Management Agency's Hazard Mitigation Grant Program and the Iroquois Gas Transmission Systems Land Preservation and Enhancement Program (LPEP), which later became the Land Enhancement and Acquisition Fund (LEAF).
  - Grants and Fundraising, Correspondence, 1991; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 1)
  - Grants and Fundraising, Lists of Sources, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 2)
  - Grants and Fundraising, Publications, 1994; 1998; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 3)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Agricultural District Maps, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 4)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Application Forms, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 5)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Board Reports, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 6)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Completed Applications, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 7)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Correspondence, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 8)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Evaluation and Ratings Forms, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 9)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Federal Emergency Management Agency Prohibition on Future Disaster Assistance, Memoranda, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 10)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Flood Plain Maps, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 11)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Guidelines, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 12)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Hazard Mitigation Planning section from Federal Emergency Management Agency Handbook, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 13)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Interim Policy Guidance, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 14)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Landowner Information Packets, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 15)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Letter of Intent, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 16)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Press Release, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 17)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Real Property Summary Reports, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 18)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Sample Deed of Open Space Easements, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 19)
  - Hazard Mitigation Grant Program, Sample Project Grant Proposal, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 20)
  - Iroquois Gas Transmission System, Funding Plaque, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 21)
  - Iroquois Gas Transmission System, Publications (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 22)
  - Iroquois Gas Transmission System, Land Preservation & Enhancement Program (LPEP) & Land Enhancement and Acquisition Fund (LEAF), Publications, Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 23)
  - Rural New York Grant Program, 1993-1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 24)
  - Schoharie Church Mission Fund, Correspondence, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 25)
- Property Files, 1986-2001; 3; 1 cubic ft.
  This series contains the files of properties owned by, under easement with, or of interest to the Schoharie Land Trust. Several files consist only of a contact checklist form, while the larger files may contain maps, photographs, deeds, easements, surveys, and correspondence. Several more complex files have been broken down into their component parts. Files are generally listed by the last name of their owner or donor or else by a more common property name such as "Schoharie Island." The Schoharie Creek property was purchased with funds from the Iroquois Gas Transmission Service's Land Preservation and Enhancement Program and more information can be found in the Grant Files series.
  - Beard, Carl, Contact Form, Correspondence, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 1)
  - Blenheim Wildlife Association, Contact Form, Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 2)
  - Bouck Falls, Correspondence, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 3)
  - Brody Property, Land Acquisition Form, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 4)
  - Dillenback Property, Correspondence, Maps, Contact Forms, 1996-1997; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 5)
  - Dillenback Property, Easement, Current Conditions Report, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 6)
  - Doleiel Property, Contact Form, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 7)
  - Feddon Property, Deed, Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 8)
  - Gray Property, Easement, 2001 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 9)
  - Harwood Property, Forest Management Plan, Easement, Baseline Conditions Report, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 10)
  - Kaplan Family Trust, Contact Form, Map, Newspaper Clipping, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 11)
  - Kittell Property, Map, Notes, Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 12)
  - Lower Mohawk Land Conservancy Property, Correspondence, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 13)
  - Mickel Property, Contact Form, Map, 1993 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 14)
  - Moore Property, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 15)
  - O Donnell Property, Easement, Photographs, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 16)
  - Paulson Property, Deeds, Tax Searches, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 17)
  - Paulson Property, Maps, 1994-1995; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 18)
  - Paulson Property, Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports, 1994-1997; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 19)
  - Paulson Property, Monitoring Report, Photographs, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 20)
  - Paulson Property, Negatives, Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 21)
  - Pickett Property, Contact Form, Maps, Correspondence, 1991; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 22)
  - Round Tuit Subdivision, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 23)
  - Sagendorf Property, Highly Erodable Land & Wetland Conservation Certification, 1986 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 24)
  - Schoharie Business Park, Generic Environmental Impact Statement, Correspondence, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 25)
  - Schoharie Creek, Construction, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 26)
  - Schoharie Creek, Correspondence, Map, 1995-1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 27)
  - Schoharie Creek, Deed, Insurance, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 28)
  - Schoharie Creek, Deed of Gift for Archaeological Rights, 2000 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 29)
  - Schoharie Creek Land Preservation & Enhancement Program (LPEP) Funding, 1991; 1993-1996; 1998 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 30)
  - Schoharie Creek, Photographs, Slides, Negatives, 1996; 2000; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 31)
  - Sharon Springs Historical District, 1993; Undated (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 32)
  - Schoharie Island, Map, Photos, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 33)
  - Squadere Property, Easement, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 34)
  - Squadere Property, Present Conditions Report, Correspondence, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 35)
  - Tepper Report, Correspondence, Reports, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 36)
  - Townsend Property, Contact Form, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Property Files), Folder 37)